# XAL [expert . analytics]

# **Curriculum Vitae for Ola Skavhaug**

### Personal information

Address: Aslakveien 31, E-mail: ola@xal.no

0753 Oslo Phone: +47 926 12 490

Born: 10.04.1974 Nationality: Norwegian

# Summary

I am a software developer, researcher, and project leader with 16 years professional experience. My main areas of technical expertise are mathematical and numerical software development, algorithm development, advanced scripting with modern scripting languages, parallel programming, software testing and deployment, library design, and scientific visualization.

Through my work, I have obtained an extensive set of skills that allows me to understand and solve challenges in collaboration with other experts. Today's industrial challenges are often multidisciplinary, and involve competences from several fields at once. A key challenge in such projects is to communicate across disiplines.

### **Technical Skills**

Languages C, C++, C++11, Java, Fortran, Python, Javascript, Perl, PHP, Bash,

Tcl/tk, Matlab, Sql, LaTeX, HTML, XML

Frameworks Numpy, SciPy, Matplotlib, MPI, BSP, Swig, Boost, Stl, Armadillo, dlib,

VTK, FEniCS, PETSc, SLEPc, Diffpack

Tools Subversion, Mercurial, Git, cvs, Make, CMake, Scons, GCC, Autoconf,

Linux, css, MySQL

### Education

2004 Dr. Scient in Computer Science, The Faculty of Mathematics and Natu-

ral Sciences, University of Oslo. Thesis' title: "Numerical Methods and

Software with Applications in Computational Finance".

1998 Cand. Scient in Computer Science, Department of Informatics, Univer-

sity of Oslo

# **Professional Experience**

2013 –	Consultant, Expert Analytics
2011 - 2013	Innovation manager at Simula Innovation
2010 - 2011	Senior Scientific Programmer at Kalkulo AS
2007 – 2010	Research Scientist and head of the computational middleware software activity at the Centre of Biomedical Computing (CBC) at Simula Research Laboratory
2005 – 2007	Research Scientist and head of the project Software for PDEs"at Simula Research Laboratory
2004 - 2005	IT-manager, Simula Research Laboratory
2004	System Administrator, Simula Research Laboratory
2004 - 2010	20% Associate Professor, Department of Informatics, University of Oslo
2001 – 2004	Ph.D. student at the Simula Research Laboratory
2000 – 2004	20% Teaching Position at the Department of Informatics, University of Oslo
2000 - 2001	Ph.D. student at the Department of Informatics, University of Oslo

# **Other Experience**

2009 - 2013	Employee representative in the board of directors, Simula Research La-
	boratory
2005 - 2006	Board member, Øraker Barnehage AS

### Languages

Norwegian Mother tongue English Fluent German Basic

### **Personal Skills**

Management Motivate and lead experts and PhD students, define and implement new projects, facilitate communication in informal surroundings to break up the work day.

Applied Analyze, develop and implement complex algorithms in applied sciences, while balancing constraints like flexibility and efficiency. Short, agile development cycles with discussions and feedback from problem owners.

### Some interests and hobbies

Physical Telemark skiing, running, biking, climbing.

Gastronomical Beer brewing, sausage making.

Other Reading, traveling, trekking, expeditions.

# **Extended descriptions of select projects**

Activity Operationalization of Enki Open Source for Statkraft

Role Solution architect and software developer

Staffing Two main developers and several researchers and students

Description Enki is an open source hydrological simulation platform initially develo-

ped by SINTEF for Statkraft over a time period of several years. The original implementation, being a proof of concept type research code, was not suited for daily use in an operational setting due to limitations on scalability, design and performance. I was hired in a project to remedy this, and we realized that we needed to reimplement everything from scratch and use the existing code base as a starting point for the algorithmic aspects. The resulting hydrological forcasting toolbox, named

SHyFT, is now run daily at Statkraft.

Tools C++11, Stl, Swig, Python, Armadillo, dlib, Boost, yaml, Codeblocks

Activity POC data analysis scripting platform for Statkraft

Role Solution architect and software developer

Staffing Project leader, data analysts, and two main developers

Description Statkraft's current analysis platform for midterm forcasting of power

markets is getting old. New technical solutions that can handle both the complexity of their models in a natural way, and also changing requirements caused by massive data growth, are therefore being considered. In the project, I contributed to the implementation of a new domain model, desiphered the binary result files from the core market simulator to populate this model with data, and then made a proof of concept analysis platform in Python that showcased some of the possibilities such tool can offer. The project was considered a success, and

released funding for planning a complete new analysis platform.

 $\begin{array}{ll} \mbox{Activity} & \mbox{mCASH backend development} \\ \mbox{Role} & \mbox{Senior Python Developer} \end{array}$ 

12-15 Python developers

Staffing

Description In this project, I have been working on most parts of the backend of a

new mobile payment system. This includes financial transaction handling, the internal bank implementation, messages emitted through various protocols based on recipients, OpenID Connect scopes implementation and payment for these, web handlers for endpoints, and Datastore transaction in the Google app engine, all in Python. I have also rewritten the instrumentation test framework, that does real life scenario, black box testing of the core system. The development is test driven, with tests covering close to 100 percent of the code base, follows the Scrum agile method, and utilizes state-of-the-art technologies like Git for version control, Nose for testing, and Sphinx for documentation.

Tools Python, Google app engine, Git, buildout, nose tests, Sphinx, webapp2,

Jinja2, OAuthLib, JSON, html, javascript, jQuery, Pusher

Activity Computational Middleware, Center for Biomedical Computing

Role Leader, scientist and software developer

Staffing 3-4 scientists and developers

Description As a project leader, I had the responsibility of the technical development,

scientific achievements, the economy, and the personnel in the project. The project strongly emphasized the development of reliable, extensible and numerical efficient software components for solving scientific pro-

blems through simulations.

Activity Software for PDEs, Simula Research Laboratory

Role Leader, scientist and software developer

Staffing 6-8 scientists, developers and PhD students for two years

Description Under my responsibility the project defined and developed novel software

frameworks for advanced computer simulation and visualization based on a hybrid technology of C++ and Python. Simula Research Laboratory applied and was awarded a Centre of Excellence by the Research Council of Norway in 2007, where the activity of this project became a central

component.

Activity Python Computing Components

Role Main developer

Description PyCC is a modern and efficient scripting framework that is used to solve

differential equations modelling the electrical activity in the human heart — the so called bidomain equations. The complexity of the problem, and the use of the tool to conduct research, requires both flexibility and efficiency. To meet these needs we implemented a high level scripting interface in Python for flexibility, and migrated bottlenecks to low-level extension modules implemented in C/C++ and Fortran. Central activities were library design, interface building strategies, cross language

techniques, code generation, and third party software integration.

C/C++, Fortran, Python, Swig, MPI, Subversion, Scons, PETSc, FEniCS, Hypre, BoomerAMG, Diffpack, GNU Compiler Collection and De-

bugger, Valgrind

Activity Viper

Tools

Role Main developer

Description Viper is a lightweight runtime visualization framework for scientific data

and results. It grants the underlying visualization library, VTK, direct access to the simulation result, thereby minimizing memory copies for efficiency. Viper can visualize both scalar and vector data, as well as

wireframe geometries (meshes).

Tools C/C++, VTK, Python

Activity Gotran

Role Main developer

Description Systems of ordinary differential equations are often complex, and imple-

menting these in a numerically efficient way is both time consuming and error prone. To remedy this, I have implemented Gotran – a compiler that takes ODEs described in a high level DSL (domain specific language) and generates highly specific and numerically efficient C/C++ code. By building on top of another software project I have implemented, Swiginac, Gotran utilizes symbolic manipulation during several of the code transformations to reduce the number of floating point opera-

tions needed to evaluate the ODE systems during simulation.

Tools C/C++, Python, Swiginac, Swig

Activity Swiginac - extending Python with symbolic mathematics

Role Main developer

Staffing Open source project with several contributors

Description Swiginac is a symbolic mathematics module for Python. It is built by

exposing GiNaC, a symbolic manipulation library written in C++ to Python with Swig. The efficiency of the underlying C++ library makes Swiginac one of the fastest technologies in its class in Python, and the possibilities of writing expressions in various ways makes Swiginac well suited for code generation purposes. Swiginac was developed as a side project during my PhD, in order to make a system for automatic code

verification of numerical simulators.

Tools C++, Stl, Python, Swig, Distutils, Subversion, Make

Activity Famms - automatic code verification for PDEs

Role Main developer

Description Standard PDE problems can be formulated as F(u)=0, where F is

a possibly non–linear system of differential equations. The task is then to find the unknown u. By selecting a manufactured, analytical solution instead, called v, we can compute b=F(v). Then by defining G=F(v)-b, we again obtain a standard problem on the form G(v)=0. Forgetting that we know v, we can try to solve the last equation to see if the numerical simulator is working as expected. The method above is commonly referred to as the method of manufactures solutions, and Famms, the software system I implemented, automates this process by calculating both b and the perturbed problem G with minimal effort.

Tools C/C++, Python, Swig, Swiginac, Diffpack, FEniCS, PyCC.

Activity Biomedical computing
Role Developer and project leader

Staffing Two developers

Description In this project, a California based software company in biomedicine wan-

ted to incorporate some of the technology I had developed into their commercial code to strengthen the finite element analysis and visualization capabilities of their software. Over a period of six months, we successfully integrated the components into their code, such that they

could use PyCC and Viper.

Activity Symphonical Role Main developer

Staffing Project leader and two developers

Description Symphonical is a web-based collaboration tool. Initially it was conceived

as a tool for running agile software development projects based on the metaphor of post-it notes on a virtual wall, a scope that since has been widened. We created the first prototype of the system, in 2005, before

it was spun out as a company and developed further by others.

Tools PHP, Mysql

Activity Gründergarasjen, Simula Innovation

Role Manager

Staffing 35 entrepreneurs working on their startups

Description Responsible for planning and implementing Gründergarasjen, a free star-

tup incubator hosted by Simula. By opening up our research laboratory for entrepreneurs, we hope to provide a creative environment in which new ideas are born and realized. The garage is loosely based on the 12 rules of the HP garage; commonly recognized to be the birth place of Silicon Valley. Entrepreneurs can stay with us up to one year, provided

they get positive evaluations.

Activity Department of Informatics, University of Oslo

Role Associate Professor

Description Over a period of ten years, I have given lectures in two popular courses

at the university, teaching students how to apply high-level computer languages for advanced problem solving, and how mix languages for

both convenience and numerical efficiency.

Tools Python, C/C++, Swig, Perl, Bash/Sh, Tcl/tk, CGI